Guide to the Catharine T. Patterson Collection of Walter Crane
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Catharine T. Patterson Collection of Walter Crane
1867-1957
GEN MSS 1386
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
12.97
12 boxes + 1 broadside
The collection contains original sketches, drawings, proof sheets, autograph manuscripts, and autograph letters from and to the English illustrator Walter Crane.
Patterson, Catharine T. (Catharine Tinker)
Ospovat, Henry, 1877 or 1878-1909
Elliott & Fry
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Catharine T. Patterson, 1956.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence, 1876-1914. II. Writings and Graphic Material, 1867-1913. III. Catharine T. Patterson Collection Files, 1920-1957.
Catharine T. Patterson (1874-1963)
Catharine Tinker Patterson was born in 1874 in Weymouth, Massachusetts, the daughter of the Reverend Anson Phelps Tinker (1844-1886, Yale 1868) and Martha Jane White Tinker (1846-1880). An 1897 graduate of Emerson College of Oratory in Boston, Massachusetts, she taught school in Minnesota and Massachusetts before joining the faculty at Emerson in 1900. From 1906 until 1917 she taught at Hartford Public High School in Hartford, Connecticut, and in 1917 settled in New York City when she married George Lewis Patterson (1869-1942), founder and president of Stanley & Patterson, manufacturers of electrical signal apparatus. After her husband's death, Catharine Patterson returned to Connecticut to live near her brother Chauncey Brewster Tinker (1876-1963, Yale BA 1899, MA 1901, PhD 1902), professor of English at Yale University from 1903 to 1945 and the first keeper of rare books at Yale University Library. She died in Hartford on September 11, 1963, and was buried in Evergreen Cemetery in Portland, Maine, with her husband and his first wife Alice Carter Patterson (1869-1915).
In an essay published in The Christian Science Monitor on July 26, 1941, Catharine Patterson described a life of collecting that began with the buttons, stones, and seashells she and her brother had saved as children. Their early adult lives took them in different directions, but they developed their passion for Walter Crane's work while traveling together in England where, she wrote, "the spell of the Pre-Raphaelites was upon us. Everything belonging to the Brotherhood beckoned us." They began by studying the paintings, drawings, furniture, stained glass, and other decorative arts created by Burne-Jones, Millais, and Rossetti, and made a special pilgrimage to Kelmscott House, the home and workshop of William Morris in the London suburb of Hammersmith. Through Morris they discovered the decorative book work of Crane, his friend and follower, in particular that which illustrated the stories the Tinkers had loved so much as children. The siblings set out to acquire books, manuscripts, letters, original drawings, textiles, and other items related to Crane, and to lend selections from their collection to public exhibitions. The earliest known loan was to the Brooklyn Museum in 1923 when "an extensive collection of books and prints and an original drawing by Walter Crane, from the collection of Mrs. George L. Patterson" were shown. A 1939 New York Public Library exhibition described their Crane collection as being "made by [Mrs. George L. Patterson] and her brother, Professor Chauncey Tinker of Yale University, who acquired a large part of it from a son of Walter Crane." The collection was shown again in 1953 at Princeton University, three years prior to its arrival at the Yale University Library.
Catharine Patterson wrote that she was delighted when she found that the collection, which she and her brother had always intended to donate to Yale, had a counterpart at Harvard University in the Caroline Miller Parker Collection of Works by Walter Crane, formed by Caroline Parker (1874-1922) and given to Harvard in 1928 by her husband Augustin H. Parker. Today the Beinecke Library's Catharine T. Patterson Collection of Walter Crane stands as the third largest collection of Crane material after the Walter Crane Archive at the University of Manchester in England and the Parker Collection at the Houghton Library.
Walter Crane (1845-1915)
Walter Crane (1845-1915), English author and illustrator best known for his work in children's literature. Among the most important illustrators of the nineteenth century, Crane was also a painter, essayist, and decorative artist who created designs for wallpapers, tiles, printed textiles, posters, stained glass, embroideries, and pottery. His formal education consisted of an apprenticeship served with the wood engraver and illustrator W. J. Linton from 1858 to 1862; later he was a founder of The Art-Workers' Guild (1884) and a founder and first president of The Arts and Crafts Exhibition Society (1888).
Scope and Contents
The collection contains original sketches, drawings, proof sheets, autograph manuscripts, and autograph letters from and to the British illustrator Walter Crane. Prominent material includes correspondence, drawings, and proofs related to Crane's commission to illustrate A Wonder Book for Girls and Boys, by Nathaniel Hawthorne (Boston: Houghton, Mifflin & Company, 1893), and a group of unpublished illustrated storybooks he created for his children Beatrice, Lionel, and Lancelot. Other correspondents include Crane patrons Ethel Alec-Tweedie and Catharine Lorillard Wolfe, and colleagues such as Elkin Mathews, William Morris, Charles Rowley, and David Croal Thomson. Also present is an autographed portrait photograph of Crane by Elliott & Fry of London, a painted silk fan, embroidered and batik-dyed textiles, and a full-color preparatory drawing of his Vineyard wallpaper pattern. The collection also holds a bookplate designed for Crane by Henry Ospovat (1877-1909).
Series III consists of files holding Catharine T. Patterson's documentation of her collection. They contain correspondence with dealers and institutions, inventories, research notes, and clippings, as well as her writings on Crane and on her collection. Also present is her copy of A Bibliography of First Editions of Books Illustrated by Walter Crane, by Gertrude C. E. Massé (London: The Chelsea Publishing Co., 1923), with her annotations to record her acquisitions of books and related drawings.
Artists -- Great Britain; Illustrators -- Great Britain; Children's literature -- Illustrations; Illustration of books -- Great Britain; Illustration of books -- United States; Mythology, Classical -- Juvenile literature; Children's literature -- 19th century; Illustrations (layout features) -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Sketchbooks -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Studio portraits -- England -- 19th century; Artists -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Illustrators -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Alec-Tweedie, Mrs. (Ethel), -1940; Crane, Beatrice, 1873-; Crane, Lancelot, 1880-; Crane, Lionel, 1876-; Crane, Mary Frances Andrews, approximately 1846-1914; Crane, Walter, 1845-1915; Huish, Marcus B. (Marcus Bourne), 1845-1921; Mathews, Elkin, 1851-1921; Morris, William, 1834-1896; Ospovat, Henry, 1877 or 1878-1909; Patterson, Catharine T. (Catharine Tinker); Rowley, Charles, 1839-1933; Thomson, David Croal, 1855-1930; Wolfe, Catharine Lorillard, 1828-1887; Elliott & Fry; Independent Order of Odd Fellows. Manchester Unity Friendly Society
- Correspondence, 1876–1914; Series I; 0.21; 1 box
  - Alec-Tweedie, Mrs. (Ethel), 1910 January 8 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ashworth, Thomas Edwin, 1894 January 25 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Brown, Ford Madox, 1888 February 24 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chapman and Hall, 1891 January 20 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Day, Lewis F. (Lewis Foreman), 1881 December 12 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Houghton, Mifflin and Company, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Scope and Contents
    Concerning production of The Wonder Book, and transporting Crane's personal property.
  - Huish, Marcus B. (Marcus Bourne), 1881, 1882 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Jones, Thomas E., 1898 January 19 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Mathews, Elkin
    - Letters from and to Crane, 1890–1906 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Ten letters and two postcards from Crane to Mathews; two letters from Mathews to Crane, most regarding the publication of Crane's Renascence (London: Elkin Mathews, 1891).
    - Letters from Mary Frances Crane and Lionel F. Crane, 1894–1895 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Maxwell, Perriton, 1914 September 11 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Morris, William, 1891 September 24 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Letter from Morris to Crane arranging for a meeting to discuss illustrations for Morris's The Story of the Glittering Plain.
  - Rowley, Charles, 1889–1911 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Includes printed "at home" card (1898-1899) and invitation to the wedding of Beatrice Crane to Sydney Jeffree (1900).
  - Scribner's Monthly Magazine (editor), 1877 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Concerning pirated edition of his The Baby's Opera.
  - Swain, Joseph, 1876 August 27 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Thomson, David Croal, 1885–1902 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Concerning his proposed articles for the Art Journal, his role as English delegate to the First International Exhibition of Modern Art at Turin, and comments on the Royal Watercolor Society's presentation to William Callow.
  - Ware, William Robert, 1892 January 18 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Concerning exhibitions of Crane's work at museums in New York and Boston.
  - Whiteford, Mr., 1901 August 9 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Concerning Whiteford's offer of Italian embroideries and costumes to the Victoria and Albert Museum.
  - Wilde, Oscar, 1888 July 1 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Unidentifed recipients, 1876–1902 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Six autograph letters, signed.
  - Autograph with monogram, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Writings and Graphic Material, 1867–1913; Series II; 13.43; 10 boxes + 1 Broadside oversize
  Arrangement
  Organized into three subseries: Manuscripts and Artwork, Printed Material, and Other Material.
  - Manuscripts and Artwork
    - Aladdin, or The Wonderful Lamp (London & New York: George Routledge and Sons, [1875]) (Box 2, Folder 22)
      One drawing, graphite and ink on paper, of Aladdin and his lamp (p. 2); on verso, graphite sketch of a procession scene (p. 4).
    - "Andromeda Perseus / Sleeping Beauty", 1878 (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 91)
      One preparatory drawing, gouache and Chinese white on brown paper, for an allegorical silver cup realized in collaboration with the illustrator George Du Maurier (1834-1896). The cup was produced by Hunt & Roskell, manufacturing and retail jewellers and silversmiths in London.
    - The Baby's Opera (London & New York: George Routledge and Sons, [1876]) (Box 2, Folder 23)
      Five drawings, watercolor on paper; illustrating the songs "Here We Go Round the Mulberry Bush" (p. 11), "How Does My Lady's Garden Grow" (p. 15), "Little Bo-Peep" (p. 37), "I Had a Little Nut Tree" (p. 45), and "Jack & Jill" (p. 53).
      [Note: Francesca Tancini questions their authenticity (to Crane's hand); the drawings are reversed when compared with the finished result and with the original drawings at the British Museum, Whitworth Art Gallery, and the Opie Collection at Bodleian Library.]
    - "Bellona", undated (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 96)
      One drawing, gouache on brown paper.
    - [A Book for Beatrice], 1880 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      Thirty-one graphite and watercolor drawings pasted into a sketchbook. Inscribed on flyleaf: "These drawings were made for my sister Beatrice when a little girl - date 1880 - by my late Father Walter Crane R. W. S. signed Lionel Crane." Known as: A Book for Beatrice.
    - "A Book for Lionel", [1881-1882] (Box 2, Folder 25)
      Fifty-one graphite and watercolor drawings pasted into an album with boards covered with flowered paper. Attached is Lionel F. Crane's typewritten note, signed and dated "Melcombe House Montpellier Row | October 16/40": "This is an original book, drawn and written by my Father, Walter Crane, containing 56 drawings [sic], one of the famous black books, done for us when we were children and cleaned and restored and mounted by my wife, Winifred Crane, Signed Lionel F. Crane | Oct 16/40." Some of the drawings could have been colored or altered in some way by Lionel and Winifred Crane.
    - "A Boy's Book of the Alphabet", [1881] (Box 2, Folder 26)
      Thirty-six graphite and watercolor drawings pasted into a sketchbook. Leaf laid in: "This book was done by my late Father…for me when a child signed Lionel F. Crane."
    - The Forty Thieves (London & New York: John Lane, [1898]) (Box 2, Folder 27)
      One drawing for the cover; red and black ink on paper.
    - "His Babyship", [1910-1911] (Box 2, Folder 28)
      Autograph poem, possibly for an unpublished book "His Majesty the Baby."
    - "His Majesty the Baby", [1910-1911] (Box 2, Folder 29)
      Six loose drawings, graphite and ink on paper, inserted in a blank bound sketchbook; also known as "His Majesty's Servants."
    - "The House that Art Built", 1890 (Box 8, Folder 100)
      Sixteen ink and watercolor drawings in an oblong sketchbook bound in gray paper boards; inscribed by Crane on inside front cover: "Lancelot Crane 1890."
    - "The House that Jack Built up to Date", 1904 (Box 2, Folder 30)
      Four leaves with autograph manuscript, illustrated, for a skit written by Crane and performed by members of the Art Workers' Guild at Clifford's Inn, January 26, 1904; in tan wrappers.
    - Household Stories from the Collection of the Brothers Grimm (London: Macmillan Co., 1882), circa 1881 (Box 2, Folder 31)
      One drawing, ink on Bristol board, for "Rapunzel."
    - "Ivy's King Aelfred's Album of Music", 1901 (Box 9, Folder 105)
      Cover design, watercolor on paper.
    - "Lancelot's Levities Limned by Walter Crane", 1884 October (Box 2, Folder 32)
      Seventy-two ink and watercolor drawings tipped into album (99 leaves, 42 of which are uncut), dated on front cover Oct 1884; only partially published in Little Folks (London, 1888). Bound in half cloth, and with Crane's bookplate.
    - "Lionel Francis Crane His Book", 1880 April (Box 2, Folder 33)
      Thirty-three graphite and watercolor drawings pasted into a sketchbook. Inscribed on flyleaf: "This book was drawn for us when we were children - by my late Father Walter Crane R.W.S. signed Lionel F. Crane." In tan wrappers.
    - "Lionel His Primer and Copy Book", 1879 (Box 2, Folder 34)
      Sketchbook of 39 leaves with graphite drawings. The first half of the book is designed as a copy book, with Crane's drawings at the top of the sheet and Lionel's copies on the bottom. The second half of the book contains alphabet letters with accompanying images.
    - Menu design for a dinner to honor William Poel, December 1, 1912 (Box 8, Folder 101)
      Ink on card, accompanied by a proof print on blue paper.
    - "Mr. Michael Mouse Unfolds his Tale"
      - Sketch, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
        One sketch, graphite and watercolor on tracing paper.
      - Drawings, undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
        Album bound in boards covered with flowered paper, holding ink and watercolor drawings: 18 drawings for "Mr. Michael Mouse Unfolds his Tale, and "The True Tale of a Mouse, Continued" (17 drawings), "A Bat Sat in a Hat" (8 drawings), and "The History of Bronwen the Brown, Harlech 1887 (15 drawings) for a total of 58 drawings on 70 leaves.
        First and second stories published as Michael Mouse Unfolds his Tale, Reproduced from the Original Manuscript in the Collection of Mrs. Catharine T. Patterson (New Haven: Yale University Library, 1956).
    - "Omnium Gatherum", 1909 (Box 8, Folder 102)
      Design, gouache on board, for the cover of the University of London Bazaar & Fete booklet, edited by Mrs. Alec-Tweedie; inscribed along lower edge: "This is the original by Walter Crane for my Bazaar booklet. E. Alec-Tweedie."
    - "Poems", 1867–1881 (Box 3, Folder 37)
      Album of autograph poems with vignette illustrations (dated 1867-1872) and a graphite portrait of Mary Frances Andrews Crane (dated June 25, 1881) tipped in on verso of leaf 1; 140 leaves (64-140 blank). Bound in vellum, with Crane's bookplate. Several of the poems were published in Crane's Renascence (London: Elkin Mathews, 1891).
    - Renascence, A Book of Verse (London: Elkin Mathews, 1891)
      - "Renascence", 1893, undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
        Autograph poem on paper mounted on board, accompanied by Crane's autograph dated April 26, 1893.
      - Headpiece and tailpiece, ink on paper, circa 1890 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - The Shepheard's Calender, by Edmund Spenser (New York and London: Harper Brothers, 1898)
      - Binding design, circa 1897 (Box 3, Folder 40)
        Watercolor and Chinesea white on board.
      - Endpaper design, circa 1897 (Box 3, Folder 41)
        Watercolor and Chinesea white on paper.
      - Proof sheets, circa 1897 (Box 3, Folder 42)
        For title pages and decorative borders.
      - Printed pages and page spreads, circa 1897 (Box 3, Folder 43)
      - Printed binding, circa 1897 (Box 3, Folder 44)
      - Catharine Patterson's portfolio, circa 1897 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - "The Signs of the Zodiac", 1881 (Box 3, Folder 46)
      Fourteen graphite and watercolor drawings pasted on 16 leaves in a sketchbook, undated (date on title page is not contemporary with drawings), supposedly [1881]. Inscribed on title page" "These original drawings were done by my late father...signed Lionel F. Crane." Bound in gray wrappers.
    - "The Skeleton in Armour", 1883 (Box 10 (Oversize))
      Four sketches, ink and graphite on board, for a six-panel mural frieze designed for Catharine Lorillard Wolfe as a room decoration for Vinland, her Scandinavian-style house at Newport, Rhode Island. The theme was taken from Henry Wadsworth Longfellow's poem "The Skeleton in Armour," which was inspired by Longfellow's viewing of an ancient stone tower in Newport.
    - Sketchbook, 1863 (Box 3, Folder 47)
      Notebook of graphite and watercolor drawings: 40 leaves (one of which is cut off, and first and last leaves pasted to cover) with autograph notes, sketches and drawings, dated: January 21, April 30 1863. Contains several preparatory drawings for Mrs. Henry Wood, Mrs. Halliburton's Troubles and one preparatory drawing for St. Agnes Eve ; drawings copied from Henry Shaw, Dresses and Decorations of the Middle Ages, Thomas Hope, The Costumes of the Ancients, and Charles Wilkes, Narrative of the United States Exploring Expedition. Bound in three-quarter roan.
    - Spenser's Faerie Queene. A Poem in Six Books (London: G. Allen, 1894-1897), circa 1895 (Box 4, Folder 48)
      Six graphite sketches for illustrations, two ink drawings for headings for Book II, Canto IX and Book VI, Canto IX, and one ink drawing for the frontispiece, Book II, Canto X, Stanza 70 (p. 471: "But Guyon all this while his booke did read…"); Crane used himself as model in the latter drawing.
    - Stories of Old; or, Bible Narratives Suited to the Capacity of Young Children, by Caroline Hadley (London: Smith, Elder & Co. 1863), 1862 (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 98)
      Drawings for "The Story of the Birth of Moses" ("Moses in the Bulrushes") and "The Destruction of Pharaoh" ("Pharaoh's chariots and his host hath he cast into the sea"); ink on paper mounted on paper. The drawings were not used in that publication or in the American issue (New York, Sheldon & Co., 1863).
    - "Time's Show, Undoubtedly the Greatest on Earth", circa 1888 (Box 8, Folder 103)
      Seven ink and watercolor drawings, including cover, for an unpublished children's book, in an oblong sketchbook with seventeen leaves. Inscribed on front flyleaf: "These drawings are by my late Father Walter Crane R. W. S. Signed Lionel F. Crane."
    - Valentine and Orson, 1874, 1897 (Box 8, Folder 104)
      Design for cover (London & New York: John Lane, [1897]), ink and watercolor on paper, and one illustration (London & New York: George Routledge and Sons, [1874]) of "a great she-bear came up, and carried off one child), ink on Bristol board. On verso of cover drawing: "This is an original drawing by my late Father Walter Crane signed Lionel F. Crane."
    - "Vineyard" wallpaper design, 1911 (Box 11 (Broadside Oversize))
      Preparatory drawing in chalk, gouache, and Chinese white on brown paper, for "Vineyard" (also known as "Peacock and Vine with Poppies") produced by Jeffrey & Co.
    - The Vision of Dante, by Elizabeth Harrison (Chicago: Chicago Kindergarten College, 1894), 1892 (Box 4, Folder 49)
      "Dante and the Three Beasts" and "The Angel in the boat approaching Dante and Virgil on the short"; ink on card.
    - A Wonder Book for Girls and Boys, by Nathaniel Hawthorne (Boston: Houghton, Mifflin Company, 1893)
      - Two sketches on tracing paper, one gouache drawing, and a printed version for "Edition de luxe" half-title., circa 1892 (Box 4, Folder 50)
      - Thirty-one watercolor, ink, and Chinese white drawings for headpieces, tailpieces, and a half-title., circa 1892 (Box 4, Folder 51-52)
      - Two watercolor sketches for illustrations, circa 1892 (Box 4, Folder 53)
      - Twenty-six illustration proofs printed on watercolor paper; one with hand-applied color, circa 1892 (Box 4, Folder 54)
      - Seven illustration proof prints, circa 1892 (Box 4, Folder 55)
      - Five illustration proofs printed in color, circa 1892 (Box 4, Folder 56)
      - Ten proof prints, circa 1892 (Box 9, Folder 106)
        Includes proofs of binding design.
      - Proof print of end papers, circa 1892 (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 97)
      - Proof pages with text, headpieces, and tailpieces, circa 1892 (Box 4, Folder 57)
      - Printed binding, 1893 (Box 9, Folder 107)
      - Printed prospectus, 1892 (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - Unidentified projects
      - Monogram designs for "MFA"; ink on paper, undated (Box 4, Folder 59)
      - Sketch for a prospectus; graphite and ink on paper, undated (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Printed Material
    - The Book of Wedding Days (London: Longmans, Green and Co., 1889) (Box 9, Folder 112)
      Proof page for January, featuring cherubs on ice skates.
    - Bookplates, undated (Box 4, Folder 61)
      Designed by Crane for Gardner Teall and Harry Elkins Widener; accompanied by a proof print of a bookplate designed for Crane by Henry Ospovat (1877–1909).
    - "Caliban," from Eight Illustrations to Shakespeare's Tempest, 1893 (Box 9, Folder 108)
      Designed by Walter Crane, engraved & printed by Duncan C. Dallas (London: J. M. Dent, 1893). Accompanied by printed title page and the Dallastype plate of "Caliban," and the edition statement page signed by Crane and Dallas.
    - Columbia's Courtship: a Picture History of the United States in Twelve Emblematic Designs (Boston: L. Prang Co., 1892) (Box 4, Folder 62)
      Set of twelve proof prints with printer's color key blocks along the edge of plate 1.
    - "Flora's Feast" wallpaper, undated (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 92)
      Fragment of wallpaper featuring images pirated from Crane's Flora's Feast, a Masque of Flowers (New York: Cassell & Company, 1889).
    - Four Winds Farm, by Mrs. Molesworth (London: MacMillan Co., 1887), circa 1886 (Box 4, Folder 63)
      Plate (p. 47), "Now for our dance…"
    - Headpieces and tailpieces, undated (Box 4, Folder 64)
      Includes a design for the Arts & Crafts Exhibition Society.
    - Headpieces and tailpieces, undated (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 99)
    - Houghton Mifflin and Company, undated (Box 4, Folder 65)
      Catalogue with cover designed by Crane.
    - Independent Order of Odd Fellows, Manchester Unity Friendly Society, 1904 (Box 4, Folder 66)
      Past provincial grand master certificate engraved by Emery Walker.
    - Independent Order of Odd Fellows, Manchester Unity Friendly Society, 1904, 1909 (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 93)